Tufts Veterinary News UP176
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Tufts Veterinary News
1979 -- 1986
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Cummings School of Veterinary Medicine
UP176
0.25 Linear Feet
80.8 Megabytes 14 PDFs
This collection contains issues of Tufts Veterinary News, published by the Cummings School of Veterinary Medicine at Tufts University.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
This collection is organized chronologically in one series.
Biographical / Historical
The School of Veterinary Medicine was established in 1978, opened in 1979, and graduated its first class in 1983. Established through the advocacy of President Jean Mayer, the school was unique in its affiliation to a health sciences complex rather than to a school of agriculture. The school is located on a 634 acre campus in Grafton, Massachusetts, site of a former state mental hospital. The school also shares facilities with the medical and dental schools on the downtown Boston campus, where vet students receive their first year of instruction in the basic sciences. Students at the veterinary school are exposed to care of all types of animals including food (cattle, sheep, swine, goat), fiber (sheep, llama), companion (dog, cat), and sporting (horse) animals. In addition, students are given the option of learning about care for wildlife through the wildlife medicine program. In addition to medicine, surgery, preventive medicine, and public health, the school also educates students about ethics, conservation medicine, and human-animal relationships.
Initial discussions on the establishment of a veterinary school were begun in the early 1970s as the absence of such a school in the New England region combined with a prediction of a nationwide deficit of veterinarians made the need apparent. After a variety of options were explored, including locating a school at the Otis Air Force base on Cape Cod, Tufts, under Jean Mayer's leadership, stepped forward to take the lead in the project. Richard B. Talbot, dean of the College of Veterinary Medicine at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University was brought in as interim dean to oversee the startup of the school on a part-time basis. On April 29, 1978, the trustees voted to establish the school as part of Mayer's vision of an integrated "one medicine" program embracing the totality of medical, dental, veterinary, and nutrition education.
The school provides clinical facilities as part of the Tufts-New England Veterinary Medical Center, which includes the Foster Hospital for Small Animals, the Large Animal Hospital, the Cornelius Thibeault Equine Clinic, the Amelia Peabody Pavilion, the Issam Fares Equine Sports Medicine Program, the Harrington Oncology Program, and the Wildlife Clinic at Grafton, as well as the Marine Biological Laboratory at Woods Hole, and the Ambulatory Farm Clinic based at Woodstock, Connecticut.
The degree of Doctor of Veterinary Medicine (D.V.M.) is the primary degree offered by the school, though since 1995 the school also offers a Master of Science (M.S.) in Animals and Public Policy. The school features several signature programs which offer specialized perspectives on veterinary sciences, including Wildlife Medicine, Equine Sports Medicine, International Veterinary Medicine, Ethics and Values in Veterinary Medicine, and Biotechnology and Veterinary Medicine.
Related Materials
UP104, Veterinary World, DCA
Scope and Contents
This collection contains issues of Tufts Veterinary News. It is a newsletter designed to "serve as a periodical progress report of the Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, distributed to key university personnel, veterinary students, veterinarians, and others with an interest in the development of the school," (from the masthead). Newsletter of the Tufts Veterinary School about faculty, staff, students, alumni/ae, events, and programs. It was succeeded in 1986 by Veterinary World (UP104).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Digital material was transferred by the Webster Family Library, Cummings School of Veterinary Medicine, Tufts University, 2019, accession UA-2020-014.
- Tufts Veterinary News, 1979 -- 1986; 1981 -- 1986; UP176.001; 0.25 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  Tufts Veterinary News is a newsletter designed to "serve as a periodical progress report of the Tufts University School of Veterinary Medicine, distributed to key university personnel, veterinary students, veterinarians, and others with an interest in the development of the school," (from the masthead). It was succeeded in 1986 by Veterinary World (UP104). Newsletter of the Tufts Veterinary School about faculty, staff, students, alumni/ae, events, and programs.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Tufts Veterinary News, circa 1979; UP176.000009; 4.13 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary News, 1980; UP176.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Tufts Veterinary News, Spring 1980; UP176.000010; 8.71 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary News, 1981; UP176.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Tufts Veterinary News, Winter 1981; UP176.000011; 9.03 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary News, Summer 1981; UP176.000012; 8.04 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary News, Fall 1981; UP176.000013; 9.16 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary News, 1982; UP176.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Tufts Veterinary News, Spring 1982; UP176.000014; 4.86 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary News, Summer 1982; UP176.000015; 4.79 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary News, Winter 1982 -- 1983; UP176.000016; 5.05 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary News, 1983; UP176.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Tufts Veterinary News, Spring 1983; UP176.000017; 5.42 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary News, Fall 1983; UP176.000018; 5.08 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary News, 1984; UP176.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Tufts Veterinary News, Spring 1984; UP176.000019; 5.13 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary News, 1985 -- 1986; UP176.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Tufts Veterinary News, Winter 1985; UP176.000020; 5.23 Megabytes
  - Tufts Veterinary News, Fall 1985; UP176.000021; 749.37 Kilobytes
  - Tufts Veterinary News, Winter 1985 -- 1986; UP176.000022; 5.43 Megabytes